Finding Aid for Rowe Family Papers [microform] 1840-1990
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Rowe Family Papers [microform] 1840-1990, 1840s-1940s
Rowe family.
0.3 linear feet (in 1 box)
0.7 linear feet (on 2 rolls of microfilm)
Residents of Highland Township, Oakland County, Michigan. Civil War reminiscences and other papers of James D. Rowe, soldier in the 1st Michigan Cavalry; Civil War letters of Spencer D. Lee, related family member, also in the 1st Michigan Cavalry; business records of Grant and Carrie Jackson Rowe, publishers of the Milford Times; sermons of Samuel Simpson Marquis as transcribed by Mrs. G. S. Rowe; collected materials largely concerning Milford and Highland Township history; and miscellaneous photographs and Civil War print.
852173 mf334, mf335
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was donated in several accessions beginning in 1950 by Mrs. G. S. Rowe (Donor no. 2351 ), her daughter, Mrs. Lois Rowe Maugh (Donor no. 7248 ), Joan Heiser Kramer, a niece of Mrs. Maugh (Donor no. 7575 ), Patricia Horlacher (Donor no. 8047 ) and John Hoag (Donor no. 10444 ). The collection, except for indicated items, was microfilmed in 2000.
The collection is open for research.
Originals of the collection are held by the Bentley Library.
The first Rowe to settle in Highland Township, Michigan, was Squire Washington Rowe. Rowe was born June 1, 1815 in Camillus, Onondaga County, New York, later moving with his family to Parma, Monroe County, New York. Rowe and Dolly Castle were married on March 26, 1835, and the young couple soon emigrated with other family members to Michigan, arriving in May, 1835, where they built up a large farm in Highland Township and raised their family.
In 1855 Squire Rowe built an imposing stone house known today as Stone-Rowe, registered in 1976 as a Michigan Historic Site. Rowe was a Republican and served 21 terms as supervisor of Highland Township. In the Civil War, he was a recruiting officer for the 10th Regiment, Company K, and he was appointed Captain of the 14th Infantry, with the duty to raise a regiment. However, he seems not to have succeeded in this since that group does not appear on regimental rosters. He also headed relief work in aid of soldiers' widows and orphans. In 1864 Rowe was elected to the Michigan House of Representatives, which office he still held at the time of his death on November 19, 1866. His widow, Dolly, died in 1909. Squire and Dolly Castle Rowe were the parents of eight children:
Eliza Elvira, born March 22, 1836. Eliza married Willis Smith in 1856. Smith served in the 5th Michigan Cavalry during the Civil War. The Smiths spent their lives in Milford, Michigan.
James Delos, born February 18, 1838. James attended Kalamazoo College before his enlistment in the 1st Michigan Cavalry. During the war James was wounded at both Cold Harbor and at Winchester, Virginia, where he was hospitalized for three months. In 1864 while home on furlough he married Helen Putnam of Detroit. Following the war James and Helen farmed in Highland Township. Helen died in 1920; James in 1925. James and Helen Rowe had four children: Grant S., James B. (called Burt), Lois B. (called Bertha), and George L.
In 1896 Grant married Carrie Jackson, a daughter of Isaac Jackson, the original publisher of the Milford Times. Together Grant and Carrie published and edited the Times for 46 years, and had nine children: Dorothy H., Margaret A., Carrie M. (called Marian), Lois A., Robert G., Virginia P., Ruth M., Rachel J., and Winifred S.
Grant's sister, Lois B., attended high school in Lansing and then the University of Michigan in Ann Arbor. She taught school in Duluth, Minnesota, which is where she met and married William Howard Lewis of Bangor, Wales, in 1896. Lois spent the rest of her life in Wales with William and their four children: Cedric, Selwyn, Eroica and Elaine.
The third child of Squire and Dolly Rowe was Lemuel Josiah (called Josiah), born November 3, 1840. Josiah was also a student at Kalamazoo College before enlisting in the Second Michigan Infantry. Josiah was taken prisoner at Knoxville, Tennessee. He spent fourteen months in Confederate prisons, escaped and remained at large for four weeks. He was recaptured and later escaped a second time from a prison in Alabama, wandering five weeks before reuniting with Union troops in Tennessee. Around 1872 he married Jane Ogilby. He died in 1880; Jane in 1919.
Benjamin Nelson, born December 21, 1842. Benjamin worked in Washington DC during the last years of the war. He eventually settled in California. He died in 1926.
Squire Lowell (called Lowell), born February 8, 1845. In 1875 Lowell married Amelia (Millie) Jackson, a daughter of Isaac Jackson, the original publisher of the newspaper (and an older sister of Carrie who married Lowell's nephew, Grant in 1896; see paragraph above about James and Helen Rowe's children). Lowell and Millie Rowe farmed the old Rowe homestead in Highland Township, Michigan, while operating a jewelry store in Milford. In 1884 they moved to California to join Benjamin, but returned to Milford the following year to raise Millie's young sister, Mabel, after the death of her parents. Lowell and Millie Rowe were the parents of two sons: Herbert, who died in infancy in 1892, and Clifford H. Lowell died in 1921 and Millie in 1930.
Marian Chastina, born June 1, 1847. In 1875 Marian married Henry Holmes in Milford, and they moved to Duluth, Minnesota. Lois B. Rowe, a niece, stayed with them when she taught school in Duluth.
Theodosia Maria, born August 4, 1849. In 1874 Theodosia married Dr. Alexander D. Hagadorn, formerly of Milford but later of Lansing, where the Hagadorns spent their lives. Grant and Lois Rowe, children of Theodosia's brother, James, lived with the Hagadorn family while they attended high school in Lansing.
Lucius Judson (called Judson), born April 20, 1851. Judson settled in Erie, Pennsylvania. In 1873 he married his first wife, Addie Crosby, who died in 1875 in childbirth. The child, George, lived. In 1883 Judson married his second wife, Elizabeth Dunning. They had a daughter, Adda, who was born in 1885. Judson died in 1938.
The collection is divided into three series: Rowe Family Papers, Milford Historical Materials, and Milford Times Records. The bulk of the collection consists of correspondence, genealogical material and reminiscences relating to the Rowe family. The Civil War years are particularly well documented in letters written by in-laws: William Putnam, brother of Helen; the wife of James Rowe; and Spencer Lee, who married Helen's sister, Sarah. The Milford Times Records series contains business correspondence and records of the Milford Times, a newspaper published and edited by members of the Rowe family from 1890 to 1950. Carrie Jackson Rowe, who ran the Times for 46 years with her husband, Grant, was interested in Highland County local history; her writings on historical topics, as well as the historical documents she collected, form the Milford Historical Materials series.
Subjects: Mixed Materials
American newspapers--Michigan--Milford.; Business records.; Highland (Oakland County, Mich.: Township); Kalamazoo College.; Milford (Mich.); Milford times.; Oakland County (Mich.); Phrenology.; Rowe family.; South Dakota--Blizzard, 1888.; Spiritualism--Michigan.; United States. Army. Michigan Cavalry Regiment, 1st (1861-1866); United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.
Contributors: Mixed Materials
Lee, Sarah.; Lee, Spencer D.; Marquis, Samuel Simpson, 1866-; Rowe, Carrie Jackson.; Rowe, Grant.; Rowe, James Delos, 1838-1925.
Subjects - Visual Material
Brodhead, Thornton F., d. 1862.; Dwellings--Michigan--Highland (Oakland County: Township); Highland (Oakland County Mich.: Township)--Dwellings.; Interiors.; Rowe, James Delos, 1838-1925.; United States. Army. Michigan Cavalry Regiment, 1st (1861-1866); United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.
Subjects - Sound Recordings
Journalists--Michigan--Milford.; Milford times.; American newspapers--Michigan--Milford.; Rowe, Carrie Jackson.
Contributors: Sound Recordings
Rowe, Carrie Jackson.; WJR (Radio station: Detroit, Mich.)
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Prints.; Sermons.
- Rowe Family Papers
  - Introductory Materials (Reel 1)
  - Correspondence
    The Correspondence is arranged chronologically beginning with several letters written to the patriarch of the family Squire Washington Rowe by a cousin and a nephew. There are also letters from the Civil War period, including several of James Delos Rowe's letters home, telling of his money shortage during the war and his marriage to Helen Putnam in Detroit during a 30-day furlough in December, 1864. After the war, James Delos Rowe wrote of his job teaching at a rural school in Texas Township. The collection also includes his 99-page handwritten retrospective about his Civil War experiences, based on letters he wrote to his wife, Helen, during the war. These letters have not survived as part of the collection, but there are many letters to Helen from her soldier brother, William Putnam, including some written while he was imprisoned at Camp Parole, Maryland.
    Within this series are several letters written to Grant Rowe by his mother, Helen, while he was teaching school in the Dakotas, particularly after the catastrophic Blizzard of 1888, which caused her to worry. There are also three letters of Josiah Rowe's letters written before the war: one describing a great renewal of religious interest at the college in the spring of 1860; another relating his experiences teaching school; and one telling of a visit to Mt. Vernon and the final resting place of "the immortal Washington." After the war Josiah went West for his health. One letter written by Josiah from Omaha after the war talks of his prospects there and his views on local agriculture.
    Letters written by Benjamin Rowe to his parents describe his efforts to find a job in Washington in the last months of the Civil War. He eventually found work as a clerk in three different hospitals (Lincoln General, Harewood, and the "Washington" Post), which he describes in his letters. There is one charming description of Christmas at the Harewood Hospital, written in 1865 on Christmas Day. Benjamin also eventually went West for his health. A letter written in June, 1876, from Greeley, Colorado, tells of his recent marriage to Amy Brockway; the need for Colorado farmers to fight grasshoppers; and the general fear of war with the Indians in the light of recent raids.
    The collection also contains correspondence of Rowe in-laws, particularly Spencer Lee, a brother-in-law of Helen Putnam Rowe, and his wife, Sarah Lee, during Spencer's Civil War service. These letters, written as frequently as once a week during some months of the war, offer Spencer's war news (the activity of Mosby's raiders, the fall of Richmond, Southern reaction to Lincoln's assassination and Spencer's participation in the hunt for John Wilkes Booth) and his opinions of the soldier's life (elections in camp and his appreciation of a "box of goodies" from home). There are also letters from Spencer's sister, Fanny Lee, to her sister-in-law, Sarah, on such diverse topics as hairstyle, social climbing, and local religious experiences.
    - 1840-1849 (Reel 1)
    - 1850-1855 (Reel 1)
    - 1856-1859 (Reel 1)
    - 1860 (Reel 1)
    - 1861 (Reel 1)
    - 1862 (Reel 1)
    - 1863 (Reel 1)
    - 1864 (Reel 1)
    - 1865
      - January-March 1865 (Reel 1)
      - April-May 1865 (Reel 1)
      - June-December 1865 (Reel 1)
    - 1866-1867 (Reel 1)
    - 1872-1877 (Reel 1)
    - 1883-1889 (Reel 1)
    - 1892-1897 (Reel 1)
    - 1900-1907 (Reel 1)
    - 1912-1921 (Reel 1)
    - 1935-1938 (Reel 1)
    - 1941-1946 (Reel 1)
    - Collected letters of Lois Rowe Lewis 1887-1941 (Reel 1)
  - Genealogical materials
    - Family groups: Roe/Rowe, Griffin, Brown, Shuart, Parker, Cheney, Jackson (Reel 1)
    - Individuals (Reel 1)
  - Papers 1990 (Reel 1)
    (re: induction of Carrie Jackson Rowe into Michigan Journalism Hall of Fame)
  - Newspaper clippings, re: Dakota storm of 1888 marriage of Bert Rowe, West Highland Baptist Church, Stone-Rowe House, Lone Tree, history of Milford Times (by Margaret Mastick Rowe) and obituaries of Squire Lowell Rowe, Carrie Jackson Rowe, Marian Rowe Heiser, Margaret Rowe Mastick, Robert Grant Rowe, Grant S. Rowe (Reel 1)
  - Publications, articles, sermons, speeches
    - Monographs, re: Milford Monday Literary Club, 125th anniversary of Milford, West Highland Baptist Church (Reel 1)
    - "The Rebellion" by James D. Rowe, a retrospective of his Civil War experiences written in 1912 (Reel 2)
      (referred to with his original title, "Camp Tales of a Union Soldier," in Ida Brown's Michigan Men in the Civil War)
    - Articles
      - Attributed, re: Women's Baptist Foreign Missionary Society, early memories of J. D. Rowe (with transcript), township vault at Oak Grove, Order of Eastern Star Whiting Chapter, Carrie Jackson Rowe and the Milford Times (Reel 2)
      - Unattributed, re: Rowe Family centennial reunion in 1935 Rowe family history; printing; Milford history, businesses, and certain individuals (Reel 2)
    - Sermons given by Dr. S. S. Marquis, minister at Christ Church Cranbrook January 29-June 25, 1933 (Reel 2)
      (Stenotype copies taken by Ruth Rowe)
    - Speeches, re: missions, Sunday school workers, speech made to class of 1885 re change, Milford alumni banquet, printing, Milford Monday Literary Club, "Rowe Family and the Milford Times" by Marian Rowe Heiser, talk given at Eastern Star meeting, speeches by Carrie Jackson Rowe at banquet of Girl Reserves and on 60th anniversary of Milford High School class of 1882 in, 1942 (Reel 2)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Dated (Reel 2)
    - Undated (Reel 2)
      (include letter, apparently from Confederate soldier to his mother from camp near Liberty Mills, probably written in spring/summer 1864)
  - Photographs (Reel 2)
    Lithograph of Thornton F. Brodhead, commander of the First Michigan Cavalry during the Civil War; photographs of a reunion of Gettysburg veterans of which James D. Rowe was a member; family photos; and photos of Stone-Rowe house in Highland Township.
- Milford Historical Materials
  - Historical materials (Reel 2)
  - Statements of taxable property of Highland Township, Oakland Co., Michigan (Reel 2)
  - Civil War (Reel 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Reel 2)
- Milford Times Records
  - Correspondence (Reel 2)
  - Scrapbook containing news clippings about the Rowe family and the Milford Times, 1890s-1940s (Box 2)
    (Not microfilmed)
  - Subscriptions and finances, 6 volumes (Box 2)
  - Reminiscence by Carrie Jackson Rowe about editing the Milford Times, originally broadcast on WJR, recorded, March 9, 1940, cassette tape, about 30 minutes (Box 2)